let's move now to the I/O hardware so let's
now focus on a normal computer / a laptop  so no flaps
we know that we have different types of hardware
that are usually available in a computer we have disks
or storage devices we have transmission devices
like network cards
and we have a human interface devices which
will be a screen keyboard and mouse mostly
and they exchange information basically by
sending signals for us it's mainly through
cables ok we don't really discuss wireless to much but
of course we also have wireless communication
so the question here is physically how are these
things connected how do they reach the CPU
how do they get access to the CPU and share their
I/O with the CPU? let's go through
some common concepts here so we have ports
these are the physical connection points that
allow to connect a device
we have the bus this is a set of basically wires plus a
protocol that specifies the type of messages that can
be sent on the wires for the signals that can be sent
on that wire patterns of electric voltages with different
timings these are basically the signals
and of course different types of buses have
different methods for sending signals that
can go at different speed throughput and so on and so
forth we also can connect devices let's say through
other devices so we can plug a into b b
to c and so on
and in that case we use term daisy chain for an
alternative way of transmitting the signals
through devices so it practically operates as a bus and
then we have also different type of busses
so one is the PCI which is the peripheral
component interconnect
bus this is the one that connects the processor
and memory subsystem to the fast devices and then
we have expansion busses and these are for
connecting relatively slow devices compared
to the others that I will show how this
looks like in the next slide we have controllers
so these are specific electronics that are
actually operating a port or a bus or a device
and you can basically think of
them as micro computers inside the computer
that are there to do the translation between
two different types of devices or two different
types of communication between devices
you have the serial port  controller for example which can
be a single chip you have the SCSI controller that is the
small computer system interface controller
which actually contains its own dedicated
processor microcode private memory and so
on to actuate the translation this is for example
for the storage unit for specific storage
units and these are the ways in which they
are connected
so you have here the processor and you see that
this is what I meant before that the processor
can immediately directly access cache and
memory you see that they are connected
together and they don't need to go through the
PCI bus to exchange signals while they need to
do that
when for example you want to access a disk here
through a SCSI controller or other types of controllers
so you see that to the PCI bus
the connected things are the controllers that
take care of the translation between what
is behind them and the rest
and these are as I said communicating through the
PCI bus and then you can have expansion
ones to which you connect slow devices slow from the
perspective of the computer and the processor
keyboard parallel port serial port and so on